the vietnam war and the push for u.s involvement
was a result of the gulf of tonkin incident
a lie the iraq war famously is a result of lies
wars in somalia are a result of lies
the second world war and the german invasion of
poland was a result of carefully constructed lies
that is war by media let us ask ourselves of
the complicit media which is the majority of
the mainstream press what is the average
death count attributed to each journalist
it's anton carys third man i'm uh randy credico
hello everybody radio credit go live on the fly
99.5 fm wbai.org here in new york city
also uh assangecountdowntofreedom.com and
randycritical.com you'll be able to get this show
uh and it's our assange uh countdown show which
started right here on wbai four years ago folks
four years ago and uh the situation is like very
dire right now and there's a lot of things up in
the air so we're going to continue doing these
shows here at wbai where it all started until at
least after the decision by judge uh bait zazar on
january 4th or uh when trump gives him a
pardon if he does and then we can move on to
other people that need pardons but this
is very significant because the entire
uh journalism community is at risk here if
assange is uh extradited here and put in prison
all right so i want to mention on sunday january
3rd the day before judge baithesar comes out
there there will be a press conference and a
rally at the um uk embassy on 47th street at 1
00 p.m actually 11 a.m but uh 1 p.m in somewhere
in the middle of the ocean all right so it's
11 a.m on january 3rd i'm not doing this again
and so be there it's going to be great call up
212-726-1385 for more information all right so
look we have two great guests on this show today
uh guest list that we have the two are
unbelievable we have rebecca vincent
from reporters without borders will be here uh
halfway through and right now we got someone who
was in the very first season and second season
third season fourth season earlier this year on uh
assange countdown to freedom and he is a a former
cia counter terrorism officer he's a whistleblower
he's spent time in jail he's written a million
books uh he's a hero a real great guy and gee
i've already spent five minutes john kiriakou
how you doing buddy hey it's always a pleasure
randy good to see you yeah i uh you know this is
um we're at a weird time here john as you know
uh you know what do you make of all of this talk
about trump giving assange a pardon well you know
stranger things have happened and i think that
if trump wants to to take one last swing at
his detractors and his enemies pardoning julian
assange would be a really great idea yeah
so uh so it is possible i mean you know look
we're asking a guy who has executed nine people
in the last uh month and got all those children
in cages which actually started under obama
uh but we're asking we're asking him to show
some heart uh and nils melzer has come out
and so many others have come out asking for him
for the same reason that you said it it would be
first what's the right thing to do you know
he's talking about cleaning up the house
the intelligence agencies this would be one way
to do it am i right oh yeah and you said something
in your intro that i think is so important and
bears repeating these charges against julian
assange really are an attack on the entire media
uh the entire institution of the media and one
of the great disappointments here randy is that
the new york times and the washington post and
the la times and the wall street journal and all
the others are ignoring this case if you want to
read about what julian assange is going through
if you want to read about the details of the case
and about why this is so important you have to go
to the alternative media and i think that's just
a disaster over the long term for the american
uh the american media yes well that's that's a
question here's something i wanted to ask you um
you know do do they understand what would happen
in this uh city in alexandria uh virginia you
know you you've been there before uh would you
get a fair trial there no i i've maintained
from the very beginning it's not possible
for julian to get a fair trial in the eastern
district of virginia in alexandria virginia
they call edva the espionage court for a good
reason because that's where most espionage
cases are tried and it's because no national
security defendant has ever won a case there
you know they charge stack they add felony upon
felony upon felony and they venue shop and they
charge people in the in the district where they're
most likely to be convicted and the most likely
to receive a harsh sentence that's what they've
done in this case yeah it seems so let i wanted to
you know say that people like yourself and uh and
manning chelsea manning and um and julian assange
and snowden uh whistleblowers uh you know you are
not traitors you you are you are like the ultimate
patriots in this country tell me why people think
that these are crimes and it's anti-patriotic
to do what you have done and what others have done
yeah i consider myself to be a patriot and i know
that ed snowden and chelsea manning uh consider
themselves to be patriots as well you know when
when people see the word espionage when they see
that somebody has been charged with espionage they
they recognize immediately this is this is one of
the gravest crimes with which an american can be
charged and in some cases it carries with it the
death penalty but what is espionage espionage is
is spying for a foreign country a foreign power
it's leaking classified information in order
to damage the united states whistleblowers
national security whistleblowers maintain
that it is illegal to classify a crime therefore
it's illegal to not blow the whistle when you
recognize waste fraud abuse or illegality or
threats to the public health or public safety
you're compelled to blow the whistle on your first
day as a federal employee randy you raise your
right hand in the air and you swear to protect
and uphold the constitution of the united states
against all enemies foreign and domestic i only
lament that when i put my hand in the air and i
i took that oath that i was the only
one in the room who actually meant it
right yes well you know that's that's definitely
the case uh you know i think you would have
betrayed the country if you had not stood up
is that how you feel that is exactly how i felt
and you know i i kept waiting i i became
aware of the of the torture program at the
cia in 2002 just as it was beginning and i
kept waiting for somebody to come out and
say something and then i resigned from the cia i
went into the private sector and i kept waiting
for someone to say something finally five and a
half years passed and i decided i just couldn't
wait any longer well five and a half years went
by and then you got like swept up and you knew
you didn't have a chance we're going to talk about
that later in the second half of this interview
telling the truth even when it's painful is the
right thing to do is that is that your uh ethos
it's always the right thing to do and you know
there are two components to that for me uh one
is the truth always comes out sometimes it takes a
little bit of time but the truth always comes out
and one of the things that i learned in this
whole experience and i learned it from a prominent
psychiatrist he said that whistleblowers have
a very clearly defined sense of right and wrong
more clearly defined than the general population
i don't think that's a bad thing i think that's
a good thing because sometimes things are black
and white they are right or wrong and in my case
torture was wrong in ed snowden's case uh
warrantless wiretapping was wrong you're compelled
to say something you have to say something
well you know i i think that whistleblowers
like yourself are basically a safety valve you
know when it that make noise when something
bad is about to happen or is happening do you
look at the whistleblowers in the same light
absolutely i was very happy when when uh congress
passed the federal whistleblower protection act uh
the problem with it at the time was that it
exempted national security whistleblowers
from its protections and so it was amended
a year or two ago but even then you have to
you have to check so many boxes if you're a
national security whistleblower that there
still really aren't protections no protection
this is ralph nader actually had his hand in the
uh way back in the 90s with the uh whistleblower
protection act and he says it's been watered down
uh you see all of these people that violated
it uh you've seen friends of yours swept up a
lot of them uh with the sam adams group with the
uh veteran intelligent professionals uh you know
who come out and they they've been very gutsy to
do this it's just a handful it's more difficult
now to do it am i it's difficult because uh it's
you're afraid you see what's happening to assange
it's difficult because uh you basically have
been neutralized by fear is that what you think
is happening right now oh yeah scott shane at the
new york times said that on the day of my arrest
every single one of the new york times national
security sources went silent and they stayed
silent for more than six months and that's really
what the point was the point wasn't you know
to to grab john kiriakou and send him to prison
um i was facing 45 years i ended up with 23 months
so it wasn't that it wasn't to punish me so much
as it was to frighten everybody else into silence
so if you were thinking of blowing the whistle on
something did you really want to end up like john
kiriakou you lose your job you lose your clearance
you lose your pension you lose your family
nobody wants that we're gonna talk more
about how it's affected you personally uh
john in the second half of this uh interview
um but uh someone just texted me saying that
the pro that the whistleblowers aren't the
problem uh they they are this the symptom
or the alarm for the real problems you agree
with that absolutely absolutely i agree with
that whistleblowing should be encouraged uh in
in national security and it's not it's actively
discouraged well so uh i don't see too many
lately uh coming out and blowing the whistle
uh particularly on government uh wrongdoing i mean
real wrongdoing i'm not talking about deal in uh
in the ukraine i'm talking about whistle-blowing
major stuff that's going on maybe in saudi arabia
uh what's going on right now we don't know what's
going on in afghanistan what's going on uh in iraq
we just don't know but there's got to be someone
out there that i'd like to know is the press
mainstream media doing their job no i don't think
i don't think the media are doing their jobs
uh you know we know for example and this is just
one example ken delanian from nbc and msnbc is
the chief national security correspondent in
a freedom of information act request filed
by buzzfeed's jason leopold he found that ken
dolinian at nbc was sending his stories to the cia
for clearance and comment before he was
even sending them to his own editor so
we know that that it's not uncommon for these
national security correspondents journalists to
be in bed with the cia or the pentagon or nsa
they're not independent they're not trying to
root out corruption or to get a scoop they're just
sort of going along to get along and they're all
one big happy family yeah kendallenian really
is the lowest i mean if there's anyone on the
planet that uh is emblematic of that cia program
which probably still exists operation mockingbird
it would be kendallenian and then probably barbara
starr at cnn maybe the cia's got that entire
uh you know foreign foreign entity
at cnn uh under their veil you
you know i spoke to uh uh melzer the other day
and he said that it's it's it's uh what you and
others are doing uh it's a very selfless act to
blow the whistle and it's a very uh significant
personal risk and you just like before we go to
break uh address that for a second yeah the risk
is very very high you have to go into this with
your eyes open this isn't a decision that you can
just make on a whim you have to really understand
what's going to happen to you you're going to be
arrested and as soon as you're arrested you are
automatically separated from friends and family
people run screaming from the room they don't
want to talk to you they don't want to help you
they don't want to contribute to your defense fund
they just want to be left alone you're going to
lose your job you're going to lose your pension
once you're convicted of a felony they always
charge you with multiple felonies and then they'll
drop all of them but one if you if you agree to
take a plea to one but once you have a felony you
can never get a security clearance again you can't
get a professional license you can't ever work
in the corporate world again no no company is
going to hire a convicted felon especially with a
national security conviction you lose your pension
you know and then you finally get home from prison
and what do you do you end up working at starbucks
or something and that's if you're lucky well
yeah i i understand look at thomas drake he's
working at uh you know one of the big firms but
you know he's a salesman he's not what he wanted
to do in life all right uh we're we uh um have to
go we'll be uh right back folks uh thank you john
i've traveled around this country from shore
it really made me wonder the things i
heard and saw i saw the weary farmer
a plowing sad and lonely i heard the
auction hammer just a knocking down his home
but the banks are made of marble with a
guard at every door and the bolts are stuffed
uh i'm randy credical randy credico live on the
fly assange countdown to freedom all that stuff uh
on wbai uh and go to assangecountdownfreedom.com
we've been talking with john kayaku who is a
award-winning author a pen award not just that but
you got the sam adams award you got your portrait
up somewhere i mean you take a look at your resume
the last three weeks i've had cornell west and
they had nils melzer and you and you guys have got
resumes if i were to like lay it all out we'd only
uh have like three seconds for questions so
uh i congratulate you john uh you've made an
incredible comeback you've done radio for
a few years you've written a lot of books
but you went to that hardship being charged
under the espionage can you just uh you know
what what happened that drove you in a
nutshell to blow the whistle when you got back
and put yourself in the jam that you're in yeah
uh well i had left the cia as i said uh about
five years four and a half years earlier
and um and i got a call from brian ross
at abc news who said that he had a source
who said that i had tortured abu zubaydah
i was a beta we believed was the number three in
al qaeda at the time i led his capture in pakistan
in march of 2002 i had never laid a hand on
abu zubaydah or on any other prisoner and i
told brian ross your source is either mistaken or
he's lying and the more i thought about it randy
the more i was worried that someone at the white
house was going to try to pin the torture program
on me because word had begun leaking out you
know human rights watch had written about it uh
amnesty international had written about
it the red cross had written about it
so i decided that i had waited long enough for
somebody to say something about this torture
program and i was going to go public i was just
going to just tell the truth whatever he asked
me i was just going to tell the truth and so in
december of 2007 i gave a nationally televised
interview to brian ross and it ran on abc and ran
again actually a longer version ran that night on
nightline and the rest is is history the the
very next day and this is this is where it
starts to get kind of ugly the very next day the
cia filed what's called a crimes report against me
saying that i had leaked classified information
the fbi began investigating me and they
investigated me for an entire year from december
of 2007 to december of 2008 and then they closed
the case and said that i hadn't committed a
crime they sent my attorneys something called
a declination letter where they're declining to
prosecute so i thought you know all my troubles
were over and a month later barack obama becomes
president john brennan becomes the national the
deputy national security adviser and brennan
then secretly asked the justice department to
reopen the case against me i had no idea that
for the next three years my phones were tapped
my emails were being intercepted there were uh
surveillance cars following me all over the place
and then in general wait a second this is john
brennan yeah john john brennan the guy that's on
cnn that is the avatar of of democracy that john
brennan right john go ahead i'm sorry manchester
united sarcasm great enemy of uh democracy
yes go ahead it's so ironic that this guy
is being heralded as a hero but go ahead i'm sorry
oh i'll give you more irony it wasn't just john
brennan uh it was peter strzok is the one who put
the cuffs on me and um i didn't know that and and
robert mueller created the john kiriakou task
force at the justice department to prosecute me
wow wait a second why would they be interested
in you why would miller be interested in you
uh you would think the cia would be uh brennan
went to the miller yeah john brennan had
a nixonian obsession with national security leaks
and he was determined to make an example of me
wow but i just i can't believe it when i see him
for the last four years you know he's on cnn and
msnbc nbc calls themselves leaning forward and
it's like wait do they he supported torture
am i right brennan just give a brief encapsulation
of of his politics when it came to the cia
yeah john brennan john brennan famously voted
for gus hall the communist uh party candidate for
president i did two he likes to tell people that
because he's constantly trying to prove that he's
neither a democrat nor a republican that's just
silly uh he was the only major former cia official
to sign on to the obama campaign in 2008 everybody
else had gone to hillary or to mccain and that's
why he ended up doing so well for himself
well once he became the deputy national
security adviser his next goal was to become cia
director which he got in the in the second term
and as soon as he became the cia director he began
telling everybody who would listen that he wanted
to be the secretary of defense and so that's why
he's been on on tv for the last four years yelling
about donald trump you remember in 2017 when trump
first became president it was brennan that was
on msnbc and cnn yelling about trump and saying
that he was a madman and then trump suspended his
security clearance and it became this big public
affair that was all done on purpose john brennan
did that on purpose to keep himself relevant so
that once a democrat re-entered the white house
he might be in line for something big that was
just it didn't work but that's what the plan was
well he must be happy with gina whatever her
name is yeah at the cia isn't that his protege
yes yeah gina haspel was was his protege and she
supported torture no not only did she support
torture but she actually participated in the
torture wow well john let me ask you when when you
saw this going on what did it do to your stomach
no am i you're between a rock and a hard spot you
have your colleagues there that you're friendly
with that are engaging in this and that you got
your conscience uh that you've got to deal with
what what it must have been inside such a dilemma
you know on the day that the torture
program started it was august the 1st 2002
a friend of mine who was deeply involved in it
pulled me aside in the hall i was on my way to
the cafeteria to get a cup of coffee and
he pulled me aside and he said it's begun
and i said really already and he said yeah we
began on abu zubaydah today and i said man this
is wrong wrong wrong it's a slippery slope and
somebody's going to get in trouble they're going
to kill someone and somebody's going to get
in trouble i was the only one good would it do
john if you got information i mean what were
they trying to stop i mean isn't uh us foreign
policy the result of our foreign policy many of
us believe uh have encourages terrorism i mean are
you able to put it out by getting information
out of this absolutely not absolutely not you
know the official the official answer to that
question is that osama bin laden had said that
there was another attack that was imminent and
it was going to dwarf 911. that was nonsense
we disrupted we disrupted al qaeda from the very
beginning as soon as we started bombing torabora
so there was no imminent attack the real
reason that we did it is because we needed
to to sate that that need for revenge that's what
it was it was revenge right but also there's a lot
of money involved that that's thrown out there
uh and the cia doesn't forget uh you know the i
think that is probably the driving force behind uh
this zealous movement to quiet assange and bring
him over here is is maybe what he did when it came
to exposing torture and all of that but all by cia
operatives but also um for vault seven how much
do you think that influence and angered uh the
cia brass you know he did that yeah it's one thing
to talk about a torture program it's another thing
to talk about warrantless wiretapping but vault
7's information was absolutely landscape changing
right a lot of people don't know what it is can
you give us some of the sure examples yeah sure
the vault 7 revelations were the result of of a
red well a leak i guess i can use the word leak
by a cia officer a technical officer and the
information that he leaked called the vault 7
documents are really the crown jewels of the cia's
electronic capabilities so what he told us was
for example that the cia can hack into your your
tv your smart tv and use it to eavesdrop on you
they can take over the um the electronics of
your car make you drive into a tree off a cliff
whatever they want to do i mean there
was stuff like right out of the movies
in the vault seven revelations things that we
just had no idea that the cia was able to do
wait this is this is not james bond ish uh kind
of fantasy this is true stuff i mean they cannot
do it oh yeah they're actually doing it so so
let's say look all right they're mad at him
still they are angry they want to get even
even if he gets a pardon all right and then
and and and the brits go along with they have
their own dirty laundry and interest in keeping
assange muffled uh really uh the foreign office
they got they're involved in the same crimes we're
involved in sure they're partners in crime uh so
uh you know and their intelligence uh units there
so what happens to him if he gets a pardon is he
in the if he gets out he's not in the clear i mean
there's gonna be people that have a price tag on
his head i would say yes that's true i would say
that even with a pardon i would be worried
and i think really in the event of a pardon
julian needs to get to australia as quickly as
he possibly can he'll be under very heavy police
and intelligence surveillance there but perhaps
that's what would keep him safe but otherwise
yeah i don't trust the brits i don't trust uh the
americans frankly in the event that he's pardoned
so people gonna have to be worried about the
safety people be just as rigorous and vigorous
and and supporting assange until he really gets
out of harm's way and that even with a pardon
or if he's if if the high court in britain
says all right let him go we're going to have
to continue protecting him because right now
let's be honest he's in this terrible prison
you know how bad prison conditions are you were
there is it possible that he would have access
to good health care in this country would he
have access to communicate to the outside world
what would happen to him in american prison well
first of all health care is is nearly non-existent
lots of people die in prison they
die in prison every single day
uh some prisons have uh government health
care which is you know bad it's just members
of the national uh whatever they call themselves
they wear uniforms the national health service
uh and um and they you know whatever you have they
give you a tylenol and wish you the best of luck
so uh i i wrote extensively in my second
book about problems with prison health care
uh others are private health care providers
like corizon for example they've got about 27
of the of the private prison health care contracts
in america and the way they make their money is to
not give you medication to not send you out for
an x-ray or an mri the the fewer procedures that
they approve the less medicine that they give out
the more money that they make they're a publicly
traded company and there are others too like geo
for example so there is no health care it's not
it's non-existent well private prisons are a whole
different story man that you and i can talk about
forever in the future so but uh if he ends up in
the super max he's got the sam's uh restrictions
that was going to be my second point you know the
there are these communications management units
where he'll just be completely cut off from the
outside world no television no radio no telephone
you can't write letters you can't write emails
literally no contact with the outside world and
that's what they're going to want to do i i was
in a communications management unit um and and i
ended up writing a blog that i had to smuggle
out so what they did with my in my situation
is i did have email access but my emails were
delayed five days and everything outgoing and
incoming was was checked all my letters were slid
open and read then reinserted and sealed uh and um
and my phone calls were all recorded and monitored
sometimes sometimes they were monitored you know
live as i was carrying on these phone calls
so uh there's no there's really no way to get
word out when you're in a communications
management unit they're they're going to be on
them like white on rice all right just a couple
more questions here john i mean uh i could talk
to you all day long and someone should do a ten
part series do you like to do with this like ken
burns the civil war search to just go through
the entire job yeah career i'm serious not too
much blood pressure there's so much i have like a
million more questions but you know um the um why
are they going after assange what are they
doing to assange and um what is the message uh
ultimately and what are the consequences
ultimately if in fact he is extradited
he is convicted and sent to prisons what kind of
implications do we have that's the most important
question the implication is that every member of
the press would be subject to arrest for doing his
or her job that's really the bottom line here and
that's why i'm flabbergasted that the mainstream
media haven't rallied around julian assange they
have to to save themselves they have to uh and i
think that secondarily this this is meant to
frighten everybody into self-censorship right
do you really as a reporter do you really want to
solicit that classified document on your website
do you really want to put your pgp key on your
website do you really want to encourage people to
send you internal documents because you're going
to face arrest now and if you're overseas you're
going to face extradition to the united states to
stand trial on espionage charges so what this does
is it serves to to chill the entire uh environment
in national security reporting at the very least
people are going to self-censor at the very most
the government is is creating a path by which
they can snatch a reporter domestically or
overseas and bring them back to face trial
this is an incredibly dangerous development
and it's sickening to me that the the the
reporters national security reporters around the
country aren't up in arms yeah well maybe ken
dolanian will change i'm joking that's not gonna
happen but listen this has been like the fastest
30 minutes i'm serious that i've ever gone through
seriously just like boom and there's so much more
uh but we're we'll have you back on uh i look
forward to it right after assange is either um
convicted by that judge batazar whatever uh
and sent over here that's not gonna happen i
don't think but uh or after trump gives them a
pardon we don't know there's a lot of variables
uh and nothing's conclusive yet so uh john thank
you for your service you are a hero you are a
whistleblower nils melzer considers you a hero and
a whistleblower he's a hero of mine yes he's great
and uh really uh for all your sacrifices uh that
you've made and the consequences that you've had
to suffer uh keep up the good work uh people can
uh reach you and get your books at your website
yep john kiriakou.com you spell that for people
sure it's john john kiriakou is k-i-r-i-a-k-o-u
dot com i'm glad you pronounced it right all right
nobody does nobody does i know my friend from kpfa
had a hard time with it all right and i'm sure i
don't get it right no one ever got my name right
when i was growing up credico all right so uh
thank you very much we are thank you john you're
just wonderful and we'll talk to you uh again soon
we're going to take a short break and uh we'll be
joined on the other side by rebecca vincent who
i met in uh belle morris during the first phase
of the assange extradition hearings and she's
great and she's from reporters without borders
we'll be right back folks thank you once again
john thank you good to see you again yeah you
two which side are you on which side
are you on boys which side are you on
they say in harlan county there are
no neutrals there you'll either be
a union man or a thunker j.h blair which
side are you on board which side are you on
that was uh pete seeger and i want to thank john
kiriakou he was great and joining us now here
randy medical live on the fly here on wbai 99.5 fm
in new york city also this show as you know will
be on the assange countdown to freedom website
we continue that series uh that really started
right here back in 2017 and now we got someone
i actually met earlier this year way back in
february 24th in london at the belmorisch
courtroom uh the first uh half of this
proceedings this kafka-esque set of hearings uh on
assange uh and that is rebecca vincent who's the
director of international campaigns for reporters
without borders which is known internationally as
uh reporters sans frontiers and she was great
uh you know she loaded with energy uh commitment
and uh you're really such a personality charisma
too uh rebecca thank you for joining us here
again of course randy and i would have to say the
same to you with your energy and charisma you kept
us all going in that queue in the mornings in
february very cold mornings outside uh belmarsh
yes no you too you were i'm telling you that was
thank we did have a nice crew there you stefania
marizzi and we had craig murray but of course we
needed that didn't we before we went inside uh for
that dreadful experience let's go back because
i haven't spoken to you in a long time uh to
that period what you saw then uh at belle morris
and then what you saw recently uh in uh at the
old bailey in london rebecca well february uh as
you know we were all queuing up very early every
morning to try to get access uh to the hearing so
the only way that we could do that was uh to get
into the public gallery so that of course is meant
to be for members of the public um i work for an
ngo i was there as a professional ngo observer but
from day one this judge has refused to recognize
ngos as having any legitimate role in these
proceedings she won't consider us as any different
to the public so the only way that i can do my job
is also by cueing to get into the public gallery i
mentioned that because it later became a bigger
issue in september and we'll come to that but
we're not accustomed to doing our jobs this way we
monitor trials in countries all around the world
and i have to say in february so far that had
been the most difficult proceedings uh that i
had to access ever now that got much worse months
later when we returned to the old bailey um but in
february i believe we had 20 seats in the public
gallery at the time the family usually had about
six of them so there were usually on any given
day about 14 left for the rest of us right so
i think it was about around 5 30 was the cut off
most days if you didn't get out there by 5 30
a.m there was no way you were gonna get in it was
cold it was winter weather this was a 10 a.m start
um sometimes they let us into the building a
little earlier sometimes they just arbitrarily
made us suffer the last day i think right after
you left randy there was a really cold and rainy
day that was particularly miserable they left us
out for quite a long time and then the thing is
once you were in you weren't necessarily in all
day you had to jostle and fight to kind of just
to get back into the public gallery at every
point in the day if the court rose for five
minutes we got kicked out so it created this
really um hostile darwinian attitude amongst
people that were there with legitimate reasons to
want to monitor this hearing um and of course then
on top of all of these kind of atmospheric things
then we're trying to actually get in and listen to
quite complex arguments because in february that
was both side laying out their legal arguments so
so that was quite an important week and quite full
of substance and ranging from you know extradition
law to you know to the political nature of the
offense to many things and so those were very very
long and tiring days but i have to say we thought
that was bad we thought that was uncomfortable
i would take that over you know a hundred times
uh versus what we then whoa whoa whoa are you i
know what you're going to get into that was pretty
bad what you just described i was there and i was
there on the day that it rained and i tried to get
a taxi uh yeah to the tube to get back to new york
that day that was on the 27th and i know how nasty
it was there and it was pouring and getting there
so early all right so and then that of course
was before you get to um just a minute describe
what you saw in those three days i mean you
must have been alarmed by oh oh absolutely
i mean but it was it sort of solidified already
our thinking and our position on the case because
and i think it was four days of proceedings in
the end they were there were five scheduled but
they finished in four so um i was able to to
get in just with sharp elbows i have to say
and uh quite a lot of um determination because i'm
going to get back in every day but um i was able
to systematically monitor the entire proceedings
throughout those four days and what we saw is that
the u.s government really did not seem to have any
evidence lined up for these you know outrageous
accusations that they're making against mr assange
uh and then of course that we we learned more
about that with the witness testimony in september
but i have to say in february at least we could
see him we had sight of him we were we were in a
glass box and so was he he was held and you know
we've described this many times he was held in
a glass dock at the back of the courtroom like
a violent criminal like a terrorist we were um up
above looking down from another glass box but we
could see him we had sight of him we could also
see the magistrate um judge baritzer we could see
the various lawyers on both sides we could see
what was going on we could follow proceedings
properly right because we were in the courtroom
and that is one reason i would take february over
you know right over what we then experience right
now i was there sitting next to you too or close
by uh and i could see him and it was alarming as
you just said to see him in that box i mean and he
did not look well did he randy he was clearly not
well he was clearly not able to engage properly to
follow his own proceedings properly and the judge
somewhat arbitrarily denied his uh his lawyers
application for him to come sit in the well of
the court where he can participate properly so
yeah that's what was going on that week but that
was something that as an ngo observer part of what
i'm looking at i i don't cover it in the same way
that a working journalist would so part of what
i'm looking at is is like his conditions is how
how he is how he's able to follow and i couldn't
see any of those things later in september for the
reasons that we'll get into yeah well listen i i
want i want to jump to uh september because you
went back there in september i know how bad he
looked when we were both there uh and that entire
spectacle that was going on it was you know nazi
war criminals were in open court where the lawyers
next to them at nuremberg and you know it's
you would think he was a hannibal lecter or
something the way he was uh you know in wisconsin
that glass cage it was really bizarre you know
eichmann in in israel had lawyers next to him
so let me go to september what we just went
through i haven't spoken to you you were there
you monitored it uh what and you had a hard time
tell us your experience and what you gleaned from
the whole thing well it might be worth just
briefly touching on uh what happened between
february and september as well because of course
after that weekend um at the woolwich crown court
um we had the pandemic started to take hold in
the uk and in many other countries as well and so
when the uk went into lockdown belmar prison went
into lockdown as well and so that meant that uh
assange's monthly call-over hearings started to
be impacted as well so he's required to appear
before the court once a month and it became in
his view unsafe for him to even be transferred
to the prison's video conference room because
of the lack of health and safety precautions and
of course he has a history of respiratory issues
and other health issues that put him more at risk
if he does contract covet and so we we had
all of these proceedings um you know i think
there were there were around six in between the
february week of the legal arguments and then
the several the four weeks of proceedings in
september which were the witness testimonies
case we had all of these administrative call over
hearings in between and we tried to monitor those
too um we were given phone access but it often
didn't work um and sometimes the court forgot
to add the line to the court so we were all
just on hold and when i say all of us it was
journalists who were attempting to cover it right
so few people could do anything in person during
lockdown um it was really ridiculous and so i
documented that we found published on that too
um the sort of the difficulty we had with
that and assange excuse me assange did not
appear in several of those proceedings
either because of the coveted risk so
i'm sorry yeah well i understand it yet the the
whole right now you know he's exposed like a
hundred people that got uh covered there uh before
we get into uh september uh are you concerned
about him right now uh with the spread of covet
inside belmorge we are alarmed about him right now
because as it stands for over a month now he has
been de facto you know confined almost in solitary
confinement like conditions to his cell with covet
infections dangerously on the rise all around him
not just that bellmarsh prison but on his block of
belmar's prison so at reporters without borders we
believe that he should be released full stop we
always call for this we you know we think the
case against him is politically motivated the
charges should be dropped he should be released
but this uh really underscores the humanitarian
need for his release as well and we have pointed
this out um everywhere that we can we are
trying to to pressure the uk authorities
to consider this because globally we have seen
cases where journalists have died in other
countries uh due to covid and this should not
be a risk in the united kingdom in 2020 this is
ridiculous so um yeah we're not only concerned but
we are alarmed at the conditions he's currently
being held in um so yeah we talked about the
week of legal arguments uh that was heard at
the woolwich crown court in february and then
the uh administrative call over hearings in
the intervening months then september we landed
at the old bailey london central criminal court
and if we thought things were difficult in
february i mean september we honestly we could not
you could not make up the level of hoops that they
made us jump through so uh we as reporters without
borders along with a group of other ngos who were
interested in the case tried to get accreditation
again to these proceedings were again told
by the the court and in fact by the lord
chancellor robert buckland that they basically
refused still to recognize ngos as having any rule
different to the public so we were basically told
you know try your chances with the public gallery
now that was hard enough in february as you know
but now there was coveted in the mix and so it was
used really as an excuse to even more severely
limit access to proceedings now they opened up
an overflow courtroom so there was two courtrooms
where proceedings were happening in september the
main courtroom where mr assange was being held
where the lawyers were and where his family was
able to access that public gallery and then the
overflow courtroom where a handful of journalists
and i really mean a handful were allowed to sit on
the floor looking at a television screen and you
know they were able to work there now what i was
able to access and and i will explain to you with
the difficulty that it even took to get into this
bit of the building but i was only able to access
the public gallery in that courtroom so we were
not even in the room where anything was happening
i was staring across the room probably at
least 20 feet at a small television screen
you know to see the same thing that we could
see from the public gallery up close in february
now there was also another thing that had changed
there was now a cloud video platform a video
system that journalists had been given access to
that they could from the safety and comfort of
their homes uh be able to watch proceedings
that way and do their jobs um and the court
had um before the hearing started given us
and a group of other ngos and a larger group
of political observers as well because remember
there were politicians that were also interested
in the case mps meps um but on day one of the the
hearing uh when it resumed in september the judge
had a look at that and revoked all of our access
anybody who is not an accredited journalist so she
she referenced the fact that somebody had taken
a picture from the public gallery in february
but that was not us that was not anybody there for
professional purposes i don't know who it was but
that's clearly illegal that's clearly an act of
contempt of court and that is as a professional
not how i would ever do my job anywhere and i'm
i'm certainly not going to risk a prison sentence
to sneak a photo right um but that meant that we
couldn't access this video system so then we were
left to fight again first spaces in the public
gallery but um any guesses randy how many members
of the public were let in this time i think about
six right oh that would have been a dream okay so
five max but in practice that ended up often being
two because of this mysterious situation with
vips which took two weeks to resolve actually
nearly three weeks to resolve um so there
were apparently three mysterious vips for whom
spaces in the public gallery were being held and
by public gallery i mean the one in the overflow
courtroom where you're just looking at journalists
and a small screen across a large room right um
so they would let in two people and then they
would wait each session in the morning they would
hold those seats for an hour and a half and in the
afternoon a half an hour every day and these vips
never turned up finally i ascertained um through
i had been trying for for the entire time but
finally i was able to work out um from somebody
helpful in the court system that um that these
seats were being held for diplomatic observers and
uh we had it raised with the australian high
commission who then intervened with the court
and i i believe that these diplomatic observers
did not know that these seats were being uh
withheld for them and effectively blocking access
to ngos and and the public so they were eventually
released but then at the best of circumstances
five of us were in wait is that wait a second
you know we're talking about the biggest trial
on the planet journalists all right this is a i
mean beyond significant trial the whole world is
watching this uh and except for the u.s media but
the world is watching this and she knows the judge
knows people are watching this what what's the
motivation do you think by making you go through
this obstacle course to get in to cover this
i mean so at this point i'm not going to to hold
back on this i had a little twitter rant last
week because um i the hell i had to go through to
monitor 90 seconds of proceedings in one of these
call over hearings right at this point i have to
say there is no way that this is purely a matter
of incompetence there is no way that this is a
coincidence because we have faced these barriers
at three separate courts now woolwich count
court the old bailey and westminster magistrates
court uh the common factor here is the judge who
clearly does not want uh you know a significant
degree of scrutiny of these proceedings so i will
refrain from commenting further on how you know
how these proceedings are being handled apart
from the access issues but we have categorized
this at reporters without borders as barriers to
open justice and i will have more to say after
we learned the the decision which is coming up
but what i will say is it is you know it's been
really shocking to to to learn that this is this
could pass for open justice in a modern democracy
um because it certainly hasn't been it so at every
step of the way goal posts are constantly shifting
you have to bargain your way in every day i had a
whole network of of grassroots activists helping
to to cue and to help to get me in because
they saw the value in having a professional ngo
also able to monitor proceedings so i'm really
grateful for the kindness of these activists
the public stepped in where the court failed
to to ensure that there could be any you know
professional ngo scrutiny of these proceedings so
i did not witness every second of it um i had one
or two colleagues who helped a couple of times
but we had somebody in the room for at least
part of the proceedings on most days over that
four weeks so we monitored as systematically as
we could i couldn't see assange like the camera
barely went swiveled to him and when it did it
was at such a distance that i i could not comment
on his well-being or whether he could follow you
could not see who was speaking half the time the
only reason that i could follow uh to the extent
that i did is because i had everybody's voices
memorized from february all of the various lawyers
right like this is ridiculous so if you just
walked in without this context like you did you
really couldn't follow what was going on so we did
our best but this is not how i am used to doing my
job anywhere um and it is really shocking to me
that you're talking with rebecca vincent rebecca
vincent is the director of international
campaigns for reporters without borders uh
also known as internationally and most people know
it as reporters sans frontiers our reporters since
whatever uh my spanish has uh gotten worse uh i'm
randy credical we are talking rebecca about the
whatever went on there i've had people talking
about it you know pilger talked about it he was
there watching it the whole thing they're not
even like pretend like pretend there's no window
dressing there's there's not even a semblance of a
fair trial or a fair hearing going on or at least
in my eyes do you feel that they're even like
trying to make it look like it's a real fair
trial i mean at the moment i'll kind of i'll just
focus on the open justice side of it um i possibly
more optimistically than i should i am still
hoping that somehow that justice will prevail so
we have uh we have two weeks left to see what will
happen here and of course then there there will
be an appeals process depending on the decision
here but i am still hoping that the system is not
as broken as we fear that it might be um and that
you know despite these frustrations that possibly
you know um that the the court will look seriously
at this from an objective perspective um and
from our view these these charges are inherently
political which in and of itself should be a bar
from ex for extradition from the uk but we said
that in an article he said we firmly believe
assange has been targeted for his contribution
to journalism yes and the case against them is
clearly a political application of the espionage
act you still believe that don't you absolutely
and the espionage act lacks a public interest
defense so although he's been targeted for
serious contributions to extensive public interest
reporting things that the public had the right to
know about the behavior of the us government and
other states illegal acts right um and if he's if
he is extradited to the u.s to face trial there he
cannot defend himself because there is no public
interest defense in the espionage act we have
called more broadly for that law to be reformed
um but as it stands you know i thought there
was some very very powerful testimony from many
expert witnesses there that that echoed that
as well i thought you know that's it it's not
just what's happening here but what is likely
to happen to him if he's extradited to the us
we're talking about possibly 175 years in prison
in inhumane conditions i mean he's very likely
to to face special administrative uh measures and
and this is a vulnerable individual with serious
mental health issues with physical health issues
that you know we have sometimes categorized as a
possible matter of life or death and it's because
of that um so there's many many things at stake
there's humanitarian concerns many layers of
concerns here but the the bottom line is that you
know these these charges are ludicrous and and
should be dropped in the first instance and he
certainly should not be handed over to the u.s uh
if he has no chance of of affair proceeding there
we say that in this article you see we also have
serious humanitarian concerns which makes assange
uh extradition a a you know a pos posit possible
matter of life and death you really think it's
a matter of life and death if he were to be yeah
i'm asking you yeah no but i mean i i absolutely
do because i sat through days of testimony from
medical experts that were apart from one medical
expert testifying for the prosecution we heard
days of testimony about how vulnerable mr assange
is how he suffers from from depression
how he has hundreds of suicidal thoughts
per day how he has ptsd audio hallucinations um
sleeping disorder all of these issues and when you
look at the conditions and what's reported um you
know especially if he faces special administrative
procedures that is like the harshest
possible application of solitary confinement
um that that testimony was really chilling to
me that stuck out to me more on a personal level
than anything else i heard in september
um and nobody could nobody could pretend
to the extent you know that you would fool so
many credible medical experts which is which is
what the prosecution at times tried to uh try to
insinuate but no it's shocking and that's why and
frankly it's not even just a matter of extradition
i'm worried about him in belmar's prison now not
just the covert risk but the mental health issues
especially now that he's basically being locked in
his cell because of the covered risk um last month
there was an inmate um that that committed suicide
that was a friend of mr assange is that must be
incredibly triggering for somebody suffering from
suicidal thoughts themselves you know so i've said
this many times as well if anything happens to him
here it is the full legal and moral responsibility
of the uk um and we're not out of the water yet i
think you know if they think that they're going
to expedite this and hands him over and then it
will be the u.s problem so there is the risk
of something happening to him here and that is
alarming he should be immediately released well
your your organization with a great organization
around the world they've been involved in
many cases the implications to you and to your
organization uh the does it jeopardize the future
of the first amendment free speech journalism in
general what what are the implications if in
fact they are successful in uh extraditing him
to the u.s and then putting him in prison i mean
the the implications cannot be understated this
this case is historic and i felt that sitting
in the courtroom um you probably did too
randy it just you could feel this weight um this
case will have implications for journalism and
for press freedom for years to come not just
in the united states not just in the uk but
internationally if the us government is able to
successfully persecute somebody for publishing
public interest information leaked by another
source that is going to have a chilling effect
on journalism around the world this is one
reason that i don't understand the hesitant
you know nature of many mainstream media and
reporting on this in more strong terms because
it will impact everybody it will it could
it could have the potential to completely
reshape the future climate of journalism so it
applies to everybody and not just journalists but
the public because that's that's an angle that
really doesn't get enough focus that ultimately
yes it's a matter of mr assange's rights but
it's also the public's rights to information
and if media are not able to publish information
like this it is the public that ultimately suffers
because there will be less reporting on illegal
acts by states crimes that should be prosecuted
not the person who published it we will be in the
dark as a public and less able to hold our own
governments to account so this impacts everybody's
right people need to and the media need to really
circle the wagons rather than the firing squads
because this you know ironically affects them
and their futures but they don't get it what
about the uh eu how come uh they haven't come
out more strongly uh condemning uh the uk and
the us for this process well i think there
are individual eu states that have been strong
germany for example has been stronger than most
there is interest there but i you know i think
i think it's just a matter of real politique and
nobody is quite willing to cross certain lines
in uh and how they're approaching the us and
uk on this case and i think as well that this
year of course you cannot um remove covid from
this so many countries are preoccupied with with
the pandemic um that they possibly have reduced
capacity to engage on other issues compared to
other other years more normal years right um so
i don't know but this this is one message that i'm
really trying to get across now we are in a very
critical phase now we have less than two weeks
until we learn of mr assange's fate and if the
decision is for extradition we understand that
the appeals process could be seriously expedited i
i've heard from some with with knowledge of
this side of the case that there could be
scenarios that he would actually be extradited
next year so if there's any silver lining i was
going to ask you about this the next it's it's
january 4th she's going to come out to judge
with her decision uh where will rsp be at that
point will you be covering this um i will be
trying to get into the courtroom but from what we
understand um what i've been told so far is that
there's not going to be an overflow courtroom
this time there will only be the main courtroom
and so journalists are already being told that
they cannot physically access proceedings that
they can only access the cloud video platform now
the court will not give us access to this video
platform which means the only way we can get in is
a public gallery but in september if we're talking
about the main courtroom only assuming they only
let in uh the same number of people that they did
before that means only the family would be able
to access the public gallery in the main courtroom
so no journalist present no members of the
public no ngo observers we're very likely
uh to to find out this historic you know uh
decision just based on the very few people
which again they're people so immediately
connected only only the family and only the
lawyers they'll have to inform the rest of us and
i guess those journalists who are able from home
to watch the remote proceedings but if i can't get
in i will be outside the courtroom um but we are
making our position quite clear as we speak to
the court again and to the uk authorities and
i will continue to raise the open access issues
um you know as far as we can you know even after
these proceedings conclude because i have been
shocked at how the uk has really handled these
issues i in fact several weeks ago i was back
in turkey even under lockdown conditions to
monitor a hearing there and you know this is a
country that does not have nearly as strong of a
legacy as a uk in things like free expression
and rule of law but i have no problems getting
into court there to do my job they understand
the role of professional ngo observers so i've
compared that sometimes to what we face here i
will be raising these issues far beyond this case
for a long time but um as it stands they don't
want us there i'm telling you when you keep it
so any last words i know trump is has been
pressured by people in his own party and from
folks like niels melzer and sarah palin about
giving him a pardon are you hopeful uh would
you urge him to give him a pardon i can't say that
i'm hopeful because i'm i'm very cynical about uh
trump's approach to this case but i would urge him
to we have called on him to as reporters without
borders if he if he can do anything on the way
out the door to improve his terrible press freedom
legacy it would be to to pardon julian assange
to pardon edward snowden um and if that doesn't
happen we will then be urging president-elect
biden in office uh to to consider his own position
there and to to drop these charges that's
what it should come down to um these charges
shouldn't exist in the first place so a pardon is
insufficient in that regard but the most important
thing is to get him out of prison immediately
and then the other issues can be picked up so
any means of getting him out and um ensuring his
health ensuring that his life is protected that is
the immediate urgent concern well well uh you get
the last word there well actually i'd like to uh
let people know how they reach you or reach your
organization uh to stay attuned uh as to your work
not just with assange but elsewhere so our
website is www.rsf so reportersonfrontierrsf.org
and if you put backslash e in you'll get the
english version of the site um and you can
subscribe to the uk country updates which will
get you everything we're doing on assange and
other issues i'm also pretty active on twitter
and i try to live tweet anytime i'm doing stuff
on this case especially at court that being
said if i get into the public gallery i lose
my device while i'm in there but but i do update
as soon as i come out what is your twitter hand
rebecca underscore vincent um and you can check
the rsf twitter accounts as well because i share
things there too but um yeah we will we will be
involved in whatever capacity we can on the fourth
of january um even if it's for the first time not
in the courtroom uh but it will be a shame on the
uk's record if they carry this out uh you know
in in darkness which is what might happen wow
well thank you for uh you know your work for your
commitment and really uh staying on top of this
i know since february now even prior to that
but you've been on top of this the whole year
rebecca vincent from uh reporters without
borders uh also known of course as reporters sons
frontiers and you have been really wonderful uh
and thank you for joining us we'll have you back
in january we hope with some good news rebecca
vincent we're going to go out here i'm randy
critical randy critical live on the fly assange
countdown to freedom we're going to go out this is
marlena dietrich uh where have all the children
gone written by pete seeger see you next week
where have all the flowers gone long
time ago wherever the flowers go
young girls pick them everyone when will
they ever learn when will they ever learn
where have all the young
girls come long time passing
where have all the young girls gone long
time ago wherever the young girl's call
gone to young men everyone when will
they ever learn when will they ever
where have all the young
man gone long time passing
where have all the young men gone long time ago
where have all the young men gone gone to
soldier everyone when will they ever learn
long time ago
when the graveyard's gone long time passing
wherever the graveyard's gone long time ago
where have all the graveyards fall gone to
flower everyone when will they ever learn
when will they ever
learn
where have all the flowers gone long time
passing where all the flowers gone long time ago
wherever the flower's gone young girls picked
them everyone when will they ever learn
when will they end
so
you